Guide to the Melanie Dornier photographs, 2013-2016 RL.11523
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Melanie Dornier photographs
2013-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Dornier, Melanie
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
RL.11523
1.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 110 color inkjet prints 11 3/4 x 8 inches
Collection consists of two documentary photography series taken in India by Melanie Dornier. "Mahila Thana: All Women Police Station" is comprised of 56 color digital photographs, taken in 2016, recording daily life inside the walls of the All Women Police Station of Gurugram, Haryana. The images convey the human impacts of woman-specific crimes and social justice, and the role of the police station and its female officers as a safe haven for distressed and abused women. The 54 color digital prints in "Punch My Face: Women's Boxing in India" document the daily life and experiences of Meena Kumari, a wife, mother, daughter, police officer, and boxer, 2013-2016. All prints measure 11 3/4 x 8 inches. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts and the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture at Duke University.
Biographical Note
Melanie Dornier is a French documentary photographer who graduated in 2004 with a Masters of Education and Evaluation at the University of Pierre Mendes in Grenoble, France. In 2011 she was nominated for a Salon de la Photo of Paris Emerging Photographer award and in 2016 she received an Oxygen Award.
Dornier is the winner of the 2017 Bettye Lane Award for Feminist Photography, sponsored by the Archive of Documentary Arts and the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged in two sub-series: Mahila Thana: All Women Police Station and Punch My Face: Women's Boxing in India. Prints are in original order as assigned by photographer.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be viewed for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use, including print reproductions or distribution by any means requires the photographer's permission.
There is no use or distribution by any means of these images permitted in India until 2028.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Melanie Dornier photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2017.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Digital prints are on Hahnemühle Photo Rag Smooth 300 gr, printed with Epson 7890-8 colors using the ink UltraKrom K3.
Content Description
Collection consists of two documentary photography series by Melanie Dornier taken in India. "Mahila Thana: All Women Police Station" is comprised of 56 color digital prints. The photographs - taken during 2016 - record daily life inside the walls of the All Women Police Station of Gurugram, Haryana. The 54 color digital prints in "Punch My Face: Women's Boxing in India, document the experiences of Meena Kumari, a wife, mother, buffalo owner, police officer, and boxer, between 2013 and 2016.
In an artist's statement Dornier describes that in 2012, "...the safety issues of the Indian women and gender violence were brought to the fore by the news of the gang rape and death of a young student in New Delhi, India. Since then funding and action plans have been implemented all around the country. In Gurugram, the millennium city in the state of Haryana, it was decided to open an All Women Police Station (AWPS) as in each of Haryana's districts and this was completed in August 2015. The project 'Mahila Thana,' which is 'All Women Police Station' in Hindi, documents the daily life inside the walls of the AWPS of Gurugram."
On "Punch My Face," Dornier reflects that, "Meena Kumari was born in December 1982 to a modest rural family. Now she is reaching the end of her boxing career and she hopes to soon become a police inspector. In 2001, Meena was one of the first Indian women to become a boxer and enjoyed visibility on the international scene. Her first major fight was confronting her father who believed boxing was not a respectable activity for a woman. Despite this Meena worked harder and harder and quickly reached the national and international stage in the flyweight category (51KG). Back then, female boxers were trained with young boys due to the shortage of women in the ring...at the end of 2016 and at the end of this photo documentary, we see Meena in the first months of her third pregnancy."
Dornier is the winner of the 2017 Bettye Lane Award for Feminist Photography, sponsored by the Archive of Documentary Arts and the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts and the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture at Duke University.
Bettye Lane Award for Feminist Photography; Boxing -- India; Boxing for women; Documentary Photography -- India; Domestic violence; Family Violence; Motherhood -- India; Policewomen -- India; Rape; Women athletes -- Photographs; Women -- Violence against; Women's police stations; Haryana -- India; India -- Photographs; India -- Social conditions; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Photographs, 2013-2016
  Scope and Contents
  The 110 color inkjet photographic prints in the collection form two series: "Mahila Thana: All Women Police Station," and "Punch My Face: Women's Boxing in India." All prints measure 11 3/4 x 8 inches. A printed inventory and artist's statement is located in the box for each series.
  - Mahila Thana: All Women Police Station, 2016; .5 Linear Feet 1 box 56 color inkjet prints 11 3/4 x 8 inches
    With "Mahila Thana," meaning 'all women police station' in Hindi, Melanie Dornier documents life inside a women's police station in Gurugram, Haryana. The color digital prints were taken during 2016. According to Dornier, "in India, policewomen represent only 6.11% of the total police force, a very low figure compared to 9% worldwide. As a result, female police officers are mainly assigned on woman and child crime. Inside Gurugram's AWPS, 25 policewomen and 14 police officers are dealing everyday only with women's cases of crime, violence and divorce."
    The images convey the human impacts of woman-specific crimes and social justice, and the role of the police station and its female officers as a safe haven for distressed and abused women.
    - Case consultation, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0001)
      A female villager is coming to expose her case of sexual harassment to ACP Dhaarna Yadav.
    - Outside view of AWPS, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0002)
      CT Bhateri is leaving the police station on her scooter to go to the Civil Hospital
    - Outside view of AWPS, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0003)
      On a rainy Tuesday and men are waiting their turn outside on the doorstep of the AWPS to consult ACP Dhaarna Yadav.
    - Women Cell, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0004)
      SI Krishna in charge of the women cell while ASI Maha Ram is listening a woman who is the victim of a marital dispute. Constable Nisha brings some paper work.
    - First Report Information, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0005)
      Initially attending the AWPS women cell because of a marital dispute, this woman who is now a victim of domestic violence, comes to register an FRI with SI Raj Bala. She is accompanied by her sister.
    - Women Cell, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0006)
      SI Prem Chand and ASI Maha Ram are counseling a young mother on her marital issues. She is accompanied by her mother, her sister and her daughter.
    - Late evening help, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0007)
      An old lady comes to look for help, accompanied by her two daughters, about her alcoholic husband. CT Manju and HC Bala, in charge of the entry desk, inform her that she should register an FRI and that she would have to come back the next day.
    - SI Krishna, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0008)
      SI Krishna quickly runs outside when in a case review to ask for some additional information from her colleague.
    - Case consultation, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0009)
      ACP Dhaarna Yadav is consulting on some cases and the complainant brings some additional information to document his case. His wife has fled to a foreign country.
    - Begging, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0010)
      At the end of case review, a relative begs ACP Dhaarna Yadav to rule in his son's interest.
    - High temper, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0011)
      During a case review with ACP Dhaarna Yadav, the relatives argue.
    - Cases review, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0012)
      ACP Dhaarna Yadav is listening to arguments from both sides in mediation on marital advice.
    - Writing, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0013)
      To archive a case, two written copies have to be made. ASI Kiran is doing its fastidious exercise.
    - Portrait, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0014)
      Poonam is waiting in the hall to meet ACP Dhaarna Yadav to review her case against her father's abuse.
    - Exit, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0015)
      Victim Poonam is asked to leave the room while she argues against ACP Dhaarna Yadav's rules.
    - Women Cell, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0016)
      SI Krishna is busy with paper work while a woman is waiting to show her case of marital issue to her.
    - First Report Information, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0017)
      SI Rajbala is checking the FRI of a pupil in the interrogation room.
    - Emotional distress, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0018)
      Late afternoon, a woman enters AWPS to register her case of domestic violence. ASI Chander Kanta and ASI Reena comforted her.
    - Ghonghaat, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0019)
      The woman covers her face with her veil as expected by rural tradition (Ghonghaat). SI Krishna discloses the case of marital dispute to ACP Dhaarna Yadav.
    - Fan, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0020)
      ASI Roshaw, personal guard of ACP Dhaarna Yadav is fixing the fan during a case review.
    - Paint, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0021)
      Painting of the Interrogation room while ASI Kiran is on duty. The women seated are waiting their turn.
    - Hands' talk, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0022)
      These are the Hands of SI Krishna during a mediation session.
    - Directive, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0023)
      SHO Kailash is giving orders to ASI Kiran in the AWPS's courtyard.
    - Entry desk, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0024)
      HC Bala is conversing on the AWPS' phone.
    - ASI Chander Kanta, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0025)
      In the interrogation room, she double copies some cases.
    - Entry counter, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0026)
      CT Meena is in charge.
    - Administrative work, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0027)
      HC Munesh and CT Nisha are ordering paper work of closed cases.
    - ACP Dhaarna Yadav, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0028)
      Portrait of the ACP Dhaarna Yadav at her desk at the AWPS.
    - Entry book, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0029)
      Every visit and request should be logged in the entry book.
    - Files, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0030)
      On each case, a lot of paper work is requested by the police force.
    - Evidence, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0031)
      CT Manju is handling some evidence.
    - SHO Kailash, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0032)
      SHO Kailash is having a tea break between two interviews.
    - Paper press, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0033)
      ASI Kiran is using a screwdriver to hold her paper against the breeze of the fan.
    - Chai Wala, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0034)
      The tea vendor is serving tea at the entire police station.
    - SHO Kailash, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0035)
      SI seated at her desk, is having a phone call before going back home in the late evening.
    - Armoury, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0036)
      CT Manju is unlocking the evidence and arms room.
    - Night duty, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0037)
      CT Manju is checking the outside of the AWPS.
    - Car park, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0038)
      Women police officers are waiting to go home at night.
    - Restroom, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0039)
      CT Bhateri is resting at night.
    - Personal effects, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0040)
      In the women's rest room, some clothes and uniform are hanging.
    - Restroom, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0041)
      CT Meena and CT Manju are seated on the bed waiting to start their duties.
    - Lord Krishna, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0042)
      In a private room, a prayer was performed.
    - Earrings infection, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0043)
      In the restroom, CT Ritu is taking care of CT Kavita who has an earring infection.
    - Resting, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0044)
      CT Anju is sleeping in the restroom.
    - Police uniform, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0045)
      Members of the police force are often seen without a uniform even if they are on duty. SHO Kailash is filling in some paper work with HC Munesh and CT Suman.
    - Breakfast, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0046)
      CT Batheri and CT Nisha are having their food seated on the bed of the restroom.
    - Motherhood, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0047)
      Portrait of ACP Dhaarna Yadav and her three year old son Angad.
    - Child's room, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0048)
      Body guard of ACP Dhaarna Yadav is looking after her son Angad.
    - Inside view of AWPS, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0049)
      CT Kavita is on the courtyard of the AWPS.
    - Begging, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0050)
      A young man is begging SI Rajbala to not bring any charges against him.
    - Arrest, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0051)
      A man accused of rape spent the night in the AWPS.
    - Jail, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0052)
      ASI Suresh is answering a man accused of rape.
    - On the way to court, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0053)
      ASI Chander Kanta and CT Kawal are accompanying a defendant for his judgment.
    - Dowry harassment, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0054)
      A truck brings all valuable goods of a couple to sort out a case of dowry harassment.
    - Defendant, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0055)
      A woman was accused of fraud.
    - Inside view of AWPS, AWPS, Gurugram, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11523-P-0056)
      SI Kiran crosses the courtyard of the AWPS.
  - Punch My Face: Women's Boxing in India, 2013-2016
    Shot from 2013-2016, Melanie Dornier's series 'Punch My Face' documents Meena Kumari's daily life in Rewari, Haryana. Kumari is one of the first Indian women to become a professional boxer. Characterized by the photograper as "a wife, mother, buffalo owner, police officer and boxer," Kumari hopes to eventually become a police inspector.
    - Meena Kumari's mother, Mundi, Rewari District, Haryana, India, 2014 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0057)
      Saraswaki Devi Kumari sitting in the family house living room, proud to show her daughter's medals and trophies.
    - Meena Kumari's training, Police Academy of Haryana Sport Complex, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0058)
      Meena is training every day, early morning and late evening.
    - Meena Kumari, Police Academy of Haryana Sport Complex, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0059)
      The Haryana's boxing team is training together. The male boxers often train in the ring while females stay down.
    - Meena Kumari's punch, Police Academy of Haryana Sport Complex, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0060)
      She is practicing her punch.
    - Meena Kumari, Police Academy of Haryana Sport Complex, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0061)
      After training, Meena is taking off her hands' protection.
    - Meena Kumari and her coaches, Police Academy of Haryana Sport Complex, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0062)
      Meena Kumari is running to strengthen her body, timed by her coaches: Surrender Gulia and Sandeep Kaur.
    - Meena Kumari's sweat. Police Academy of Haryana Sport Complex, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0063)
      To lose her pregnancy weight, Meena has to wear a sweat jacket so that she is not too heavy for her boxing category of 51 KG for the 62nd All India Police Competition.
    - Breastfeeding, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0064)
      Just after practice, in her living room, Meena is breastfeeding her 9 months daughter nicknamed KuKee.
    - Train station, Delhi East Railway station, New Delhi, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0065)
      With the Haryana boxing team; Meena, her husband and their daughter will be travelling by train for more than 30 hours to the 62nd All India Police Competition.
    - Queue for medical examination, Sport Hall, Ranchi, Jharkhand, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0066)
      At the 62nd All India Police Competition, Meena Kumari along with other female boxers is queueing for a weight check and a medical examination in order to register for the competition.
    - Personal effects, Boxers' quarter, Ranchi, Jharkhand, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0067)
      At the 62nd All India Police Competition, a bra and boxing gear are lying on the bed of a female of the Haryana team.
    - Training, Sport Hall, Ranchi, Jharkhand, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0068)
      At the 62nd All India Police Competition, the Haryana boxing team is training while watching boxing matches.
    - Diaper change, Sport Hall, Ranchi, Jharkhand, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0069)
      At the 62nd All India Police Competition, Meena is changing her daughter. Sitting next to the ring encouraging her team, with her husband, Sunil.
    - Hug, Sport Hall, Ranchi, Jharkhand, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0070)
      At the 62nd All India Police Competition, Meena is hugging her daughter before entering the ring.
    - Meena Kumari and her female boxing coach Matma, Sport Hall, Ranchi, Jharkhand, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0071)
      At the 62nd All India Police Competition, the referee is checking Meena's boxing gear before the start of the match.
    - Meena's Boxing match, Sport Hall, Ranchi, Jharkhand, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0072)
      At the 62nd All India Police Competition, it is the first time that Meena is competing after her maternity leave.
    - Boxing corner, Police Academy of Haryana Sport Complex, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0073)
      At the 64th All India Police Competition, Meena is taking advice from her coach Surrender Gulia and boxing friend Pinki.
    - Boxing Match, Police Academy of Haryana Sport Complex, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2015 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0074)
      At the 64th All India Police Competition, Meena wins the match.
    - Meena Kumari and family, Sport Hall, Ranchi, Jharkhand, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0075)
      At the 62nd All India Police Competition, Meena, Sunil and KuKee are leaving the competition after Meena's defeat.
    - Jharkhand, India, 2015 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0076)
      At the 64th All India Police Competition, Meena wins her 10th nationwide gold medal in flyweight category.
    - Kukee, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2015 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0077)
      Inside the house, Meena's daughter is playing with her mother's gold medal from the 64th All India Police Competition.
    - The trunk of medals, Mundi, Rewari District, Haryana, India, 2014 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0078)
      Meena's mother in the family house is digging in a large trunk to find all of her daughter's medals.
    - Sunil Kumar, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2014 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0079)
      In the bedroom, Meena's husband is taking a picture of the recent magazine article of Meena to post it on social media.
    - Interview, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2015 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0080)
      On the doorstep of her house, Meena is giving an interview to local press about her victory at the 64th All India Police Competition.
    - Preparation for boxing competition, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2015 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0081)
      In her living room, Meena is preparing herself for boxing competition around her husband, Sunil and their daughter, KuKee.
    - Rest time, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0082)
      In her courtyard, Meena is playing with Kukee, her daughter.
    - School, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2016 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0083)
      Meena is going to pick up her daughter KuKee from school.
    - Housing Core, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2013 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0084)
      In her kitchen, late evening, Meena is washing the dishes.
    - Respect for her father-in-law, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2015 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0085)
      Meena is sitting in her living room, when her father-in-law enters the room. She jumps to hide behind the curtain. Her friend, Poonam, gives her a scarf to cover herself. By tradition, she has to cover herself in front of the elders of her in-laws.
    - Womans' talk, Police quarter, Madhuban, Haryana, India, 2015 (Box 2, Image RL.11523-P-0086)